Eastman mss. II, 1869-1981 LMC 2427
Lilly Library
- IV. WRITINGS AND WORKS
  - The Word Game
    - Scripts, August 1938 (Box 20)
    - Scripts, September 1938 (Box 20)
  - Other Writings
    - "A party of labor and science", 1938? (Box 20)
    - "A question to the National Review (letter to William F. Buckley),", 1958-1962 (Box 20)
    - "A sensible utopia", 1951 (Box 20)
    - "A. J. Grinbergs", 1964 (Box 20)
    - "American culture (laughter)," undated (Box 20)
    - "The anarchists and sentimental leftists (Steffens)", 1945-1960 (Box 20)
    - "Answer to 'Socialism and Human Nature,'", 1942 (Box 20)
    - "Articles on psychoanalysis", 1915 (Box 20)
    - "Arts and people, beasts and bees," undated (Box 20)
    - "Barmine [Alexander]", 1945-1947; (2 folders) (Box 20)
    - "To bathe or not to bathe," undated (Box 20)
    - "Benson's book," notes, 1954-1959 (Box 20)
    - "Benson's book," typescript, 1954 (Box 21)
    - "Bernard Berenson", 1952-1955 (Box 21)
    - Bible in a New Order notes and drafts, 1944-1949 (Box 21)
    - Bible in a New Order translations, undated (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "Alexander was really great," undated (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "Conflict in the realm of art," undated (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "Crusader for common sense," undated (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "Edna Millay and Vincent Sheehan," undated (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "Extra carbons of essays," undated (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon foreword and table of contents, 1964-1966 (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "How to tell a story," undated (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "Illogical duty," undated (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "Lenin's fatal mistake," undated (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "Mark Twain and socialism,", 1961 (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "Mencken's virtues and deficiencies," undated (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon notes, 1958-1973 (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "Omitted,", 1963-1964; (2 folders) (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "Sherwood Anderson's integrity," undated (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "Twelve blessed events,", 1960 (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon typescript, 1929-1966?; (3 folders) (Box 21)
    - Bull in the Afternoon "Why we love Lincoln," undated (Box 21)
    - "Carl Milles", 1959 (Box 21)
    - "Cherith prayers", 1908-1911 (Box 21)
    - "China etc.", 1947-1950 (Box 21)
    - "Churchill, Truman, Roosevelt", 1950-1954 (Box 21)
    - "College writings", 1901-1909; (Folders 1-2) (Box 21)
    - "College writings", 1901-1909; (Folders 3-4) (Box 22)
    - "Conditions in Russia", 1931-1937 (Box 22)
    - "Contemporaries and friends", 1938-1961 (Box 22)
    - "Co-ops," undated (Box 22)
    - "Debate with Sidney Hook", 1945-1949 (Box 22)
    - "Debunking semantics", 1940 (Box 22)
    - "Democracy's crisis," undated (Box 22)
    - "Dialogues for plays," undated (Box 22)
    - "Diary: Guatemala," undated (Box 22)
    - "Diary of a trip to Haiti (and Jamaica)", 1947 (Box 22)
    - "Did you know that?", 1959 (Box 22)
    - "Dolphins", 1962-1967 (Box 22)
    - Early works, 1900-1905; (4 folders) (Box 22)
    - Eliena Krylenko's eulogy, 1957? (Box 22)
    - "Enjoyment of philosophy," undated (Box 22)
    - "Facing a new era", 1941-1942 (Box 22)
    - "Facts re: Russia and communists", 1945-1951 (Box 22)
    - "The failure of the socialist experiment," undated (Box 22)
    - "The Ferreros," undated (Box 22)
    - "Feuerbach" notebook, undated (Box 22)
    - "For review of Ashley Montague and other books", 1953 (Box 22)
    - "Freeman book reviews", 1953-1954 (Box 22)
    - "Fukuzawa", 1965? (Box 22)
    - "The German ideology", 1940? (Box 22)
    - "Going Places (a collection of travel essays)", 1923-1955 (Box 22)
    - Hawaii, 1962-1966 (Box 22)
    - "H. G. Wells," Bernard Shaw," undated (Box 23)
    - How Human are Animals?, "Animal motherhood,", 1957-1958 (Box 23)
    - How Human are Animals?, "The courtship of animals,", 1958-1959 (Box 23)
    - How Human are Animals?, research and notes, 1956-1957 (Box 23)
    - How Human are Animals?, typescript, undated, (3 folders) (Box 23)
    - "How I became an islander" and other Vineyard Gazette articles, 1945-1951 (Box 23)
    - "How much will we take? America's foreign policy", 1955 (Box 23)
    - "Humor", 1952 (Box 23)
    - "The importance of having fun," undated (Box 23)
    - "In my opinion", 1944? (Box 23)
    - "In Russia", 1923-1924 (Box 23)
      Includes Russian passport
    - "Jack Alan Robbins anthology," draft, undated, (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - "Jack Alan Robbins anthology," notes and correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 23)
    - "James B. Pratt about 'The Poet's Mind,'", 1908? (Box 23)
    - Japan (Fuji), 1965; (3 folders) (Box 23)
    - Kinds of Love reviews, 1931 (Box 23)
    - "The labor union bureaucracy", 1955-1956 (Box 23)
    - "Lenin's testament", 1956 (Box 23)
    - "List of names", 1943-1959? (Box 23)
    - Loose typescript pages (unidentified), undated (Box 23)
    - "The lost art of walking," undated (Box 23)
    - Lot's Wife "Bible poem,", 1942-1950 (Box 23)
    - "Louis Untermeyer, Thomas Baldwin", 1950-1981 (Box 23)
    - "Love and friendship," undated (Box 23)
    - "M. E. reader," undated (Box 24)
    - "McCarthy and anti-McCarthy", 1956-1957 (Box 24)
    - "Makhayski", 1904-1942 (Box 24)
    - Manuscript notes, undated, (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - "Market economy arguments", 1952-1963 (Box 24)
    - "Mayans, past and present", 1941-1944 (Box 24)
    - "Melville", 1964? (Box 24)
    - "Mercury book reviews", 1941-1942 (Box 24)
    - "Method of instruction," undated (Box 24)
    - "Millesgarden", 1948-1952 (Box 24)
    - "MIT architecture", 1949-1952 (Box 24)
    - "Modernism", 1951-1964 (Box 24)
    - "Modern art", 1949-1956 (Box 24)
    - Modern Monthly, 1933? (Box 24)
    - "Morals and politics", 1944-1954 (Box 24)
    - "More goods and fewer people", 1952 (Box 24)
    - My Tragic Love annotated typescript, 1951 (Box 24)
    - My Tragic Love final revisions, 1960 (Box 24)
    - My Tragic Love notes and research, undated (Box 24)
    - My Tragic Love revised typescript, 1959-1960 (Box 24)
    - My Tragic Love second carbon of revised copy, 1960 (Box 24)
    - My Tragic Love unrevised typescript, undated (Box 24)
    - My Tragic Love yellow carbon, undated (Box 24)
    - "National minorities in Russia", 1945; (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - "New fight for freedom," undated (Box 25)
    - "Non-communicative art: a rebuttal," undated (Box 25)
    - Non-Communicative Art "My own contributions,", 1950 (Box 25)
    - Non-Communicative Art notes and drafts, 1956-1959; (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - Non-Communicative Art research, 1954-1965 (Box 25)
    - Non-Communicative Art sequel, 1955-1960 (Box 25)
    - "Non-Communicative Art" reprints, 1954 (Box 25)
    - "Norman Thomas, Rockwell Kent", 1933-1936 (Box 25)
    - "Notes for (and about) fellow travellers", 1954-1956 (Box 25)
    - "Notes on Marxism", 1912 (Box 25)
    - Notes on poetry, 1966?; (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - "On improving the immortals," undated (Box 25)
    - "On things that go together," undated (Box 25)
    - "On translation," undated (Box 25)
    - "Other lives," undated (Box 25)
    - "Part V: Rovings", 1955?; (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - Poems and the Poet typescript, undated (Box 25)
    - Poems set to music by Herreshoff, undated (Box 25)
    - "Poems to enjoy - an anthology", 1939 (Box 25)
    - "Poet's almanack", 1929-1937; (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - Poland, 1943 (Box 25)
    - "Population", 1960 (Box 25)
    - "The pragmatic meaning of pragmatism", 1908; (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - "Present opinions", 1949-1955 (Box 25)
    - Published articles, 1909-1919; (Folder 1) (Box 25)
    - Published articles, 1909-1919; (Folders 2-3) (Box 26)
    - Published articles, 1920-1966; (9 folders) (Box 26)
    - "Published poems," undated (Box 26)
    - "Published in French", 1957? (Box 26)
    - "The qualities of Plato (my Doctor's thesis)," undated, (2 folders) (Box 26)
    - "Re: dirty words", 1968? (Box 26)
    - "Re: Ezra Pound and T. S. Eliot", 1933-1949 (Box 26)
    - "Re: fame," undated (Box 26)
    - "Re: literature in Russia (adventures of a monkey)," undated (Box 26)
    - "Re: National Review,", 1961-1963 (Box 26)
    - "Re: Ruth Fischer", 1944 (Box 26)
    - Remarks on various writings, undated (Box 26)
    - Russian poems and prose, 1920? (Box 26)
    - "Sacco and Vanzetti", 1927-1961 (Box 26)
    - Sicily, undated (Box 27)
    - "Silver treasury of English verse", 1952 (Box 27)
    - "Socialism etc.", 1942-1948 (Box 27)
    - "Sophomore year", 1901-1902 (Box 27)
    - "Stalin", 1945-1953 (Box 27)
    - "Stop gambling with liberty," undated (Box 27)
    - "The substructure of freedom", 1946-1951 (Box 27)
    - "Technocracy", 1932? (Box 27)
    - "They captured the rainbow", 1940? (Box 27)
    - "Thoughts, people, places", 1967 (Box 27)
    - "To answer in New Leader,", 1932-1952 (Box 27)
    - "To preserve civil liberties," undated (Box 27)
    - "Torture in the USSR", 1949? (Box 27)
    - Towards Liberty drafts and notes, undated, (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - Towards Liberty notes, 1912-1913 (Box 27)
    - Two Kinds (Fire and Water), 1928 (Box 27)
    - "Variety - metaphysics," undated (Box 27)
    - Various essays, articles, and reviews, 1920-1959; (Folders 1-5) (Box 27)
    - Various essays, articles, and reviews, 1920-1959; (Folders 6-9) (Box 28)
    - Various poem drafts, 1907-1941 (Box 28)
    - Various radio appearances, 1937? (Box 28)
    - Various unpublished anthology research and notes, undated (Box 28)
    - "Vashti's Rebellion", 1933?; (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - "Venus Bolshevik", 1917? (Box 28)
    - "What are we fighting for?", 1940-1941 (Box 28)
    - "Witch hunt", 1951-1955; (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - "World Federation", 1943 (Box 28)
- V. SPEECHES AND LECTURES
  - "Art lecture," undated (Box 28)
  - "The art of enjoying poetry", 1945-1955; (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - "Art (Twain and Tolstoy): Whitman Fellowship", 1911 (Box 28)
  - "Art Young, Dudley and Doris's wedding, on board ship," undated (Box 28)
  - "Circulars re: lectures", 1951? (Box 28)
  - Columbia lecture notes, 1907-1911; (6 folders) (Box 29)
  - Contracts, 1924-1935 and 1949; (2 folders) (Box 29)
  - "The feminist movement", 1913?; (2 folders) (Box 29)
  - "'Heritage' takes", 1959 (Box 29)
  - "Humor lecture", 1912-1937 (Box 29)
  - "Labor speeches", 1913-1953 (Box 29)
  - "Lectures: America looks ahead," undated (Box 29)
  - "Lectures - Bolshevik," undated (Box 29)
  - Legal and financial correspondence, 1931-1949 (Box 29)
  - "Liberalism lecture", 1931-1932 (Box 29)
  - Mark Twain speeches, 1954; (2 folders) (Box 29)
  - "Planning for victory", 1942 (Box 30)
  - "Poetic or practical?," undated (Box 30)
  - "Poetry in the age of science," undated (Box 30)
  - "Roll call of the martyrs", 1949 (Box 30)
  - "Russia's foreign policy and how to meet it", 1948-1950; (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - "The Russian soul and the Bolsheviks (and other lectures about Russia)", 1929-1930 (Box 30)
  - "Russia and the fight for democracy", 1918-1941 (Box 30)
  - "Science and the future of literature," undated (Box 30)
  - "Sex lecture", 1931-1933 (Box 30)
  - "Signposts on the road to serfdom", 1945-1947 (Box 30)
  - "Speech at American Federation of Labor", 1948 (Box 30)
  - "Speeches on socialism", 1912?; (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - "Stalin's foreign policy", 1946 (Box 30)
  - "Suffrage speeches (complete)", 1910-1917; (3 folders) (Box 30)
  - "Suffrage speeches (incomplete)," undated, (3 folders) (Box 30)
  - Various speeches and lectures, 1917-1966; (Folder 1) (Box 30)
  - Various speeches and lectures, 1917-1966; (Folders 2-5) (Box 31)
  - "War speeches", 1917 (Box 31)
  - "Why we laugh like human beings", 1927 (Box 31)
- VI. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Eliena Krylenko Eastman and Max, 1955 (Box 31)
  - Florence Deshon, undated (Box 31)
  - Fuller family, 1969 (Box 31)
  - Max Eastman, undated (Box 31)
  - "Saved news-pix of people kept in Max's des", 1955-1964 (Box 31)
  - Yvette Szekely Eastman, 1958? (Box 31)
- VII. MISCELLANEOUS
  - "Animals in art and poetry: Eliena's anthology", 1940-1952 (Box 31)
  - "A trip to Mexico" by Eliena Krylenko, 1940? (Box 31)
  - "Charmion: 'Fiction' about a day in the valley," undated (Box 31)
  - "Clippings on poetry", 1949-1968 (Box 31)
  - "Eliena about her father," undated (Box 31)
  - "Etudes materialistes", 1947-1952 (Box 31)
  - "Examples", 1953-1965 (Box 31)
  - "Funny," undated (Box 31)
  - "My financial career", 1930-1946 (Box 31)
  - "Pictures of poets", 1916-1968 (Box 31)
  - Poem to Max by Waldo Pierce, undated (Box 31)
  - Poem by Joe Freeman, 1962 (Box 31)
  - Printed material, 1931-1966 (Box 31)
  - "Quotations", 1935-1960 (Box 31)
  - "Saved clippings", 1950-1957; (2 folders) (Box 31)
  - Yvette Szekely Eastman's correspondence, 1969-1974 (Box 35 (Oversize))
  - Drawing of "Frosting" the dog, undated (Ovflat 32)
  - Handkerchief, undated (Box 48 (Oversize))
- VIII. AUDIO-VISUAL
  - Poetry Reading, Part II, undated (Box 46)
  - "KNDI Radio - Honolulu-Hawaii, Library Materials," uhdated (Box 46)
  - Memorial service, 7" reel, 19 May 1969 (Box 46)
  - Memorial service, 19 May 1969 (Box 46)
- VIX. JOURNALS, DIARIES, AND PUBLICATIONS
  Note: materials in this series are grouped together based on conservation and space needs rather than content. The vast majority fall either in the "Other Writings" subseries of the Writings series or the Personal series.
  - "In Russia," undated (Box 36-43)
  - "A Book Begun", 1915-1916 (Box 36-43)
  - "College Diary - Freshman Year", February-June 1901 (Box 36-43)
  - "End of 1905 (with Mrs Suzie) to Sept. 4, 1909" (Box 36-43)
  - "Journal of Thoughts (at home and at college)", October 1903-December 1905 (Box 36-43)
  - "Verses and Thoughts", 1921-1925 (Box 36-43)
  - "The Story of Morgan, Anstice, Crystal, and Max Eastman", 1883? (Box 36-43)
  - "The Christian party began with...," undated (Box 36-43)
  - Family scrapbook, early 20th century? (Box 36-43)
  - 1: "Paris-Germany", 1922 (Box 44)
  - 2: "Eastman General," memorandum book, undated (Box 44)
  - 3: "Considerations on Painting," undated (Box 44)
  - 4: "Peter (cont.), E. F. Wheeton (cont.), A. Pinchot," undated (Box 44)
  - 5: "Oberlin," undated (Box 44)
  - 6: "Vita Nuova," undated (Box 44)
  - 7: "Notes about Growth (at Columbia),", 1906-1907 (Box 44)
  - 8: "Musical Basis," undated (Box 44)
  - 9: "Beechers," undated (Box 44)
  - 10: "Einstein," undated (Box 44)
  - 11: "Recollections at Glenora, Canandaigua, (E. S. Wheaton) West Bloomfield; Talk with Peter at Erie," undated (Box 44)
  - 12: "While at Columbia," undated (Box 44)
  - 13: "Conversations with: Peter, Anna Fraser (Washington Gladden on T.K.B.), Dr. Anna Stuart, Mrs. Horner Billigs, Adra – Lois, Jervis Langdon, Dr. Hamilton, Mrs. Druman", 1937? (Box 44)
  - 14: "Stevenson's Letters", 1909? (Box 44)
  - 15: "Humanism," undated (Box 44)
  - 16: "Lecture on Iliad, Plato and Platonism, Plato Himself," undated (Box 44)
  - 17: "1927" (Box 44)
  - 18: "Eastman-Ford genealogy," undated (Box 44)
  - 19: Mercersburg journal, 1902 (Box 44)
  - 20: Address book, undated (Box 44)
  - 21: "Address book discarded June 1942" (Box 44)
  - 22: Address book, undated (Box 44)
  - 23: "France", 1924 (Box 44)
  - 24: "Max's old address books", March 1939 (Box 44)
  - 25: Address book, undated (Box 44)
  - 26: "Old addreess book," undated (Box 44)
  - 27: "Colorado Strike and criticisms of Marxism," undated (Box 44)
  - 28: Address book, undated (Box 44)
  - 29: "Psychology of Suggestion, Matthew Arnold (on Emerson)", 1906 (Box 44)
  - 30: "Eastman-Ford Genealogy 2," undated (Box 44)
  - 31: "Visit to Williamstown", October 1938 (Box 44)
  - 32: "Novel journal (in college)", 1905-1909? (Box 44)
  - 33: "Notes toward Marx & Lenin undated (Box 44)
  - 34: "In Russia - Volga Trip", 1923 (Box 44)
  - 35: "1928" (Box 44)
  - 36: "In Palestine," undated (Box 44)
  - 37: "In Russia", 1923-1924 (Box 44)
  - 38: "At 365 W. Water Street," undated (Box 44)
  - 39: "At Genoa", 1922 (Box 44)
  - 40: "France and Genoa", 1922 (Box 44)
  - 41: "Notes Toward Marx & Lenin undated (Box 44)
  - 42: "In Russia", 1923 (Box 44)
  - 43: "Psych. Treatment of Nervous Disorder," undated (Box 44)
  - 44: Military Training from the Standpoint of Educational Psychology pamphlet by Max, 1917 (Box 44)
  - 45: "Values of the Vote" and "Is Woman Suffrage Important?," addresses by Max, 1912 (Box 44)
  - 46: Woman Suffrage and Sentiment pamphlet by Max, 1914 (Box 44)
  - 47: "Word Game", 1935 (Box 44)
  - 48: "Scrapbook (when we lived in the church)," undated (Box 44)
  - 49: "Williams College", 1900-1901 (Box 44)
  - 50: "Present Trends in Russia," discussion pamphlet by Max, 1930 (Box 44)
  - 51: "Poems and Sketches", 1912? (Box 44)
  - 52: "Poems and Sketches", 1915? (Box 44)
  - 53: "Western Trip", summer 1901 (Box 44)
  - 54: "Russia Convention, Notes for Trotsky's Life," undated (Box 44)
  - 55: "In Russia", 1922-1923 (Box 44)
  - 56: "Present Trends in Russia," discussion pamphlets by Max (3 copies), 1930 (Box 44)
  - 57: The Last stand of Dialectic Materialism: A Study of Sidney Hook's Marxism pamphlet by Max, 1934 (Box 44)
  - 58: Liberator pamphlets by Max, undated (Box 44)
  - 59: "Education and Art in Soviet Russia," with foreword by Max, undated (Box 44)
  - Three woodblocks, undated (Box 44)